<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-spring-srv6-path-segment-10"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SRv6 Path Segment">Path Segment for SRv6 (Segment Routing
    in IPv6)</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Weiqiang Cheng" initials="W." surname="Cheng">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengweiqiang@chinamobile.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dhruv Dhody" initials="D." surname="Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560066</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yongqing Zhu" initials="Y." surname="Zhu">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Guangzhou</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>zhuyq8@chinatelecom.cn</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="6" month="September" year="2024"/>

    <workgroup>SPRING Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>Segment Routing (SR) allows for a flexible definition of end-to-end
      paths by encoding an ordered list of instructions, called "segments".
      The SR architecture can be implemented over an MPLS data plane as well
      as an IPv6 data plane.</t>

      <t>Currently, Path Segment has been defined to identify an SR path in
      SR-MPLS networks, and is used for various use-cases such as end-to-end
      SR Path Protection and Performance Measurement (PM) of an SR path. This
      document defines the Path Segment to identify an SRv6 path in an IPv6
      network.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Segment routing (SR) <xref target="RFC8402"/> is a source routing
      paradigm that explicitly indicates the forwarding path for packets at
      the ingress node by inserting an ordered list of instructions, called
      segments.</t>

      <t>When segment routing is deployed on an MPLS data plane, called
      SR-MPLS <xref target="RFC8660"/>, a segment identifier (SID) is present
      as an MPLS label. When segment routing is deployed on an IPv6 data
      plane, a SID is presented as a 128-bit value, and it can be an IPv6
      address of a local interface but it does not have to be. To support SR
      in an IPv6 network, a Segment Routing Header (SRH) <xref
      target="RFC8754"/> is used.</t>

      <t>In SR, a path needs to be identified for several use cases such as
      binding bidirectional paths <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-bidir-path"/>
      and end-to-end performance measurement <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-stamp-srpm"/>.</t>

      <t>Additionally, in an SR-MPLS network, when a packet is transmitted
      along an SR path, the labels in the MPLS label stack will be swapped or
      popped, so no label or only the last label may be left in the MPLS label
      stack when the packet reaches the egress node. Thus, the egress node can
      not determine from which ingress node or SR path the packet came. To
      identify an SR-MPLS path, a Path Segment is defined in <xref
      target="RFC9545"/>.</t>

      <t>An SRv6 path could be identified by the content of a segment list.
      However, the segment list is not be a good key identifier, since the
      length of a segment list is flexible according to the number of required
      SIDs. Also, the length of a segment list may be too long to be a key
      when it contains many SIDs. For instance, if packet A uses an SRH with 3
      SIDs while Packet B uses an SRH with 10 SIDs, the key to identify these
      two paths will be a 384-bits value and a 1280-bits value, respectively.
      Further, an SRv6 path cannot be identified by the information carried by
      the SRH in reduced mode <xref target="RFC8754"/> as the first SID is not
      present.</t>

      <t>Furthermore, different SRv6 policies may use the same segment list
      for different candidate paths, so the traffic of different SRv6 policies
      are merged, resulting in the inability to measure the performance of the
      specific path. However, each SRv6 policies may need to measure the
      segment list in its own candidat path, and this is independent with
      other SRv6 policies. Without a Path ID to specify the path will cause
      the statistic of the traffic from multiple paths using the same segment
      list under different SRv6 policies merge into an aggregated result on
      the egress endpoint node.</t>

      <t> </t>

      <t>To solve the above issues, this document defines a new SRv6 segment
      called the "SRv6 Path Segment", which in total is an 128-bits value, to
      identify an SRv6 path.</t>

      <t>When the SRv6 Path Segment is used in reduced mode SRH <xref
      target="RFC8754"/>, the entire path information is indicated by the Path
      Segment, and the performance will be better than using the entire
      segment list as the path identifier, while the overhead is equivalent to
      the SRH in normal mode. Furthermore, with SRv6 Path Segment, each SRv6
      candidate path can be identified and measured, even when they use the
      same segment list.</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>PM: Performance Measurement.</t>

        <t>SID: Segment ID.</t>

        <t>SR: Segment Routing.</t>

        <t>SR-MPLS: Segment Routing with MPLS data plane.</t>

        <t>SRH: Segment Routing Header.</t>

        <t>SR path: A path described by a segment list <xref
        target="RFC9545"/>. </t>

        <t>SRv6 path: A path described by an SRv6 segment list. </t>

        <t>PSID: Path Segment Identifier.</t>

        <t>PSP: Penultimate Segment Popping.</t>

        <t>Further, this document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
        target="RFC8402"/> and <xref target="RFC8986"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Use Cases for SRv6 Path Segment">
      <t>Similar to SR-MPLS Path Segment <xref target="RFC9545"/>, SRv6 Path
      Segment may also be used to identify an SRv6 Path in some use cases:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Performance Measurement: For Passive measurement <xref
          target="RFC7799"/>, path identification at the measuring points is
          the pre-requisite <xref target="RFC9545"/>. SRv6 Path segment can be
          used by the measuring points (e.g., the ingress/egress nodes of an
          SRv6 path) or a centralized controller to correlate the packets
          counts/timestamps, then packet loss/delay can be calculated.</t>

          <t>Bi-directional SRv6 Path Association: In some scenarios, such as
          mobile backhaul transport networks, there are requirements to
          support bidirectional paths. Like SR-MPLS <xref target="RFC9545"/>,
          to support bidirectional SRv6 paths, a straightforward way is to
          bind two unidirectional SRv6 paths to a single bidirectional path.
          SRv6 Path segments can be used to correlate the two unidirectional
          SRv6 paths at both ends of the path. <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-bidir-path"/> defines how to use PCEP and
          Path Segment to initiate a bidirectional SR path.</t>

          <t>End-to-end Path Protection: For end-to-end 1+1 path protection
          (i.e., Live-Live case), the egress node of an SRv6 path needs to
          know the set of paths that constitute the primary and the
          secondary(s), to select the primary packet for onward transmission,
          and to discard the packets from the secondary(s), so each SRv6 path
          needs a unique path identifier at the egress node, which can be an
          SRv6 Path Segment.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="SRv6 Path Segment">
      <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC8986"/>, an SRv6 segment is a 128-bit
      value.</t>

      <t>To identify an SRv6 path, this document defines a new segment called
      SRv6 Path Segment. An SRv6 Path Segment MUST NOT used for routing so it
      MUST NOT be copied to the IPv6 destination address. <xref
      target="RFC8754"/> states that the SR segment endpoint node creates
      Forwarding Information Base (FIB) entries for its local SIDs (without
      constraining the details of implementation). In order to provide a new
      independent 128-bit ID space for Path Segment, the Path Segment is
      required to be stored seperate from the other SIDs (for example in a
      different table from the FIB).</t>

      <t>Depending on the use case, an SRv6 Path Segment identifies:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>an SRv6 path: A PSID is used for identify a segment list. On the
          egress node, the statstics of this path will be identified by its
          PSID.</t>

          <t>a set of SRv6 paths: A PSID can be used to identify a bundle of
          SRv6 paths as an aggregated path in measurement when multiple
          segment lists use the same PSID. On the egress node, the statstics
          of these paths will be merged and identified by this PSID.</t>

          <t>a Candidate-path in a SRv6 Policy <xref target="RFC9256"/>: All
          the segment list within this Candidate-path use the same PSID. On
          the egress node, the statstics of this Candidate Path will be
          identified by this PSID.</t>

          <t>an SRv6 Policy: All the segment lists within all the Candidate
          Paths in the SRv6 policy use the same PSID. It this case, the
          statistic of traffic under this SRv6 policy will be merged by using
          the same PSID on the egress node.</t>
        </list>In other words, a SRv6 PSID can be used for a segment list, or
      multiple segment lists, or all the segment lists in a Candidate path, or
      part of or all the Candidate path in an SRv6 policy, depending on the
      need of use cases.</t>

      <t>Moreover, a segment list may be allocated more than one PSID if
      needed. For example, the same segment list in different Candidate Path
      or SR policy can use different PSID. In this way, the traffic in
      different Candidate Path or SR policy can be differentiated even when
      they are using the same segment list.</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Format of an SRv6 Path Segment">
        <t>This document defines two formats of the SRv6 Path Segment. A
        future document MAY add further new formats for the SRv6 Path Segment,
        provided the SRv6 PSID value remains unique irrespective of the
        format.</t>

        <t/>

        <section title="SRv6 Path Segment: Locator and Local ID">
          <t>As per <xref target="RFC8986"/>, an SRv6 SID consists of
          LOC:FUNCT:ARG, where a locator (LOC) is encoded in the L most
          significant bits of the SID, followed by F bits of function (FUNCT)
          and A bits of arguments (ARG). L, the locator length, is flexible,
          and an operator is free to use the locator length of their choice. F
          and A may be any value as long as L+F+A &lt;= 128. When L+F+A is
          less than 128, then the remaining bits of the SID MUST be zero.</t>

          <t>SRv6 Path Segment can follow the format, where the LOC part
          identifies the egress node that allocates the Path Segment, and the
          FUNCT part is a unique local ID to identify an SRv6 Path and its
          endpoint behavior, which is END.PSID (End Function with Path Segment
          Identifier). The code point of END.PSID is 100. The Argument part is
          set as 0 by default. Future use cases may define the detailed usage
          of Arguments part. </t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
 +--------------------------------------------------------------+
 |  Locator            |     Function ID  |Arg                  | 
 +--------------------------------------------------------------+
 |<-------------------------128 bits--------------------------->|

        Figure 1. PSID Format following LOC:FUNCT:ARG

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="global" title="SRv6 Path Segment: Global ID">
          <t>An SRv6 Path Segment ID can be a Global ID, and its format
          depends on the use case and out of the scope of this document.</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[             
 +--------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                         Global PSID                          |
 +--------------------------------------------------------------+
 |<-------------------------128 bits--------------------------->|
          
             Figure 2. 128-bit Global PSID
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Encoding of an SRv6 Path Segment">
      <t>This section describes the SRv6 Path Segment encoding in SRH.</t>

      <t>The SRv6 Path Segment MUST appear only once in a segment list, and it
      MUST appear as the last entry in the segment list.</t>

      <section title="SRH.P-flag">
        <t>To indicate the existence of a Path Segment in the SRH, this
        document defines a P-flag in the SRH flag field, and it is to be
        allocated, see IANA allocation section. The encapsulation of SRv6 Path
        Segment is shown below.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Next Header   |  Hdr Ext Len  | Routing Type  | Segments Left |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |  Last Entry   |     Flags     |              Tag              |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    |            Segment List[0] (128 bits IPv6 address)            |
    |                                                               |
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    |                                                               |
                                  ...
    |                                                               |
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    |          Segment List[n-1] (128 bits IPv6 address)            |
    |                                                               |
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    |    SRv6 Path Segment (Segment List[n],128 bits IPv6 value)    |
    |                                                               |
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    //                                                             //
    //         Optional Type Length Value objects (variable)       //
    //                                                             //
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 

                Figure 3. SRv6 Path Segment in SID List
]]></artwork>
          </figure><list style="symbols">
            <t>P-flag(TBA1): set when SRv6 Path Segment is inserted. A node
            that does not understand the P-flag will ignore it as described in
            <xref target="RFC8754"/>. A node that understands the P-flag but
            does not support SRv6 Path Segment processing MUST ignore the
            P-flag. If the P-flag is unset or the P-flag is ignored when
            processing, the SRv6 Path Segment processing is skipped or
            ignored.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>SRH.P-flag processing can be enabled or disabled by configuration
        on devices, it can be done by CLI, NETCONF YANG or other ways, and
        this is out of the scope of this document.</t>

        <t>The pseudo code of SRH.P-flag processing is described as below.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    S01.  if SRH.P-flag processing is enabled:
    S02.     if SRH.P-flag is set:
    S03.        SRv6 Path Segment processing       ;;ref1   

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Ref1: The SRv6 Path Segment processing is accosiated with the
        specific application, such as SRv6 Path Segment based Performance
        measurement, so this is out of the scope of this document.</t>

        <t>In order to support the intermediate nodes to process the PSID, the
        PSID value MUST be unique globally within the domain. In some use
        cases, only the egress need to process the SRv6 Path Segment,
        therefore, the P-flag processing can be done at the egress node only
        while the intermediate nodes do not need to process it. In this case,
        the PSID value can be unique only locally on the egress node. However,
        please note that, in this case, if the PSID is processed on an
        intermediate node, errors may occur due to the value conflict of
        PSIDs. This feature can be enabled by configuration like CLI , NETCONF
        YANG or other ways. In this case, the pseudo code is described as
        below.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    S01.  if SRH.P-flag processing is enabled:
    S02.    if intermediate node processing is disabled: 
    S03.        if SRH.P-flag is set and SRH.SL == 0:
    S03.            SRv6 Path Segment processing      
    S04     else:
    S05.        if SRH.P-flag is set:
    S06.            SRv6 Path Segment processing

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>When the SRH.P-flag is set, the Path Segment processing is enabled.
        In the cases that the intermediate processing of Path Segment is
        disabled, a node will process the Path Segment only when it is the
        last segment endpoint node indicating by SL == 0. In this case, when
        the nodes are an intermediate node, it will ignore the processing of
        Path Segment. When the intermediate processing is enabled, all the
        segment endpoint nodes along the path are able to process the Path
        Segment if a Path Segment is encoded in the SRH. There are some use
        cases that metadata of the packets will be collected and processed on
        the intermediate nodes, especially for the stateful use cases. The
        details of these use cases are out of the scope of this document, and
        will be described in other documents in the future. </t>

        <t/>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SRv6 Path Segment Allocation">
      <t>A Path Segment is a segment on the egress node, and it can be
      allocated through several ways, such as CLI configuration on the engress
      node, or allocated from the central controller by using BGP <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-idr-sr-policy-path-segment"/>, PCEP <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment"/> or other ways. The mechanisms
      through which a Path Segment is allocated are out of scope of this
      document.</t>

      <t>When a PSID is allocated on the egress, it MUST be distributed to the
      ingress node of the path that identified by the path segment. In this
      case, only the egress will process the PSID, and other nodes specified
      by SIDs in the segment list do not know how to process the PSID.</t>

      <t>Depending on the use case, a PSID may be distributed to the SRv6
      nodes along the SRv6 path. In this case, the SRv6 nodes that learned the
      PSID may process the PSID depending on the use case. This is out of the
      scope of this document, and may be studied in the future if needed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Processing of SRv6 Path Segment">
      <t>When the SRv6 Path Segment is used, the following rules apply:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The SRv6 Path Segment MUST appear only once in a segment list,
          and it MUST appear as the last entry. Placing an SRv6 Path Segment
          at any other location in the SID list will result in unpredictable
          forwarding behavior. Only the one that appears as the last entry in
          the SID list will be processed.</t>

          <t>When an SRv6 Path Segment is inserted, the SL MUST be initiated
          to be less than the value of Last Entry, and will not point to SRv6
          Path Segment. For instance, when the Last entry is 4, the SID
          List[4] is the SRv6 Path Segment, so the SL MUST be set to 3 or
          other numbers less than Last entry.</t>

          <t>The SRv6 Path Segment MUST NOT be copied to the IPv6 destination
          address.</t>

          <t>Penultimate Segment Popping (PSP, as defined in <xref
          target="RFC8986"/>) MUST be disabled for the penultimate Segment in
          the SRH. In other words, an SID with PSP flavor MUST NOT be used in
          the penultimate segment in the SRH to aovid removing the SRH before
          reaching the egress node.</t>

          <t>The ingress needs to set the P-flag when an SRv6 Path Segment is
          inserted in the SID List. Nodes that support SRv6 Path Segment
          processing will inspect the last entry to process SRv6 Path Segment
          when the P-flag is set. When the P-flag is unset, the nodes will not
          inspect the last entry.</t>

          <t>The specific SRv6 Path Segment processing depends on use cases,
          and it is out of scope of this document.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This I-D requests the IANA to allocate, within the "SRv6 Endpoint
      Behaviors" sub-registry belonging to the top-level "Segment-routing with
      IPv6 data plane (SRv6) Parameters" registry, the following
      allocations:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[   Value      Description                               Reference
   --------------------------------------------------------------
   100       End.PSID - SRv6 Path Segment                [This.ID]

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t>This document also requests IANA to allocate bit position TBA1 within
      the "Segment Routing Header Flags" registry defined in [RFC8402].</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   Value      Description                               Reference
   --------------------------------------------------------------
   TBA1       P-flag to indicate using Path Segment      [This.ID]

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce additional security requirements and
      mechanisms other than the ones described in <xref
      target="RFC8402"/>.</t>

      <t>Similar to SR-MPLS Path Segment <xref target="RFC9545"/>, the data
      plane processing of a PSID is a local implementation of an SRv6 segment
      endpoint node, which follows the same logic of an existing SRv6 data
      plane. </t>

      <t/>

      <t>In this document, only the egress node and the ingress node of the
      associated path will learn the information of a PSID. The intermediate
      nodes of this path will not learn it. However, in some cases, the whole
      Segment list with PSID may be used in a sub-set of a longer path. In
      this case, the whole segment list may be shared to the ingress node of
      the longer path. Similar to other SIDs defined in <xref
      target="RFC8402"/>, the PSID must be distributed in a trusted domain
      under the considerations defined in Section 8.2 of <xref
      target="RFC8402"/>. </t>

      <t>A PSID is used within an SRv6 trusted domain <xref target="RFC8402"/>
      and must not leak outside the domain; therefore, no new security threats
      are introduced compared to current SRv6. </t>

      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8402"/>, SR domain boundary routers MUST
      filter any external traffic destined to an SID associated with a segment
      within the trusted domain; this applies to a PSID as well. Other
      security considerations of SRv6 described in Section 8.2 of [RFC8402]
      apply to this document. The distribution of a PSID from an egress node
      to an ingress node is performed within an SR-trusted domain, and it is
      out of the scope of this document. The details of the mechanism and
      related security considerations will be described in other documents.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t/>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   Zhenbin Li
   Huawei Technologies
   Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
   Beijing  100095
   China

   Email: lizhenbin@huawei.com


   Jie Dong
   Huawei Technologies
   Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
   Beijing  100095
   China

   Email: jie.dong@huawei.com

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Adrian Farrel, Stefano Previdi, Zafar
      Ali, Lijie Deng, Zehua Hu, Joel Halpern, Yao Liu, Greg Mirsky, Quan
      Xiong, Weier Li and Xinyue Zhang for their valuable comments and
      suggestions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8402"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8754'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8986'
?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9256'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9545'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8660'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-idr-sr-policy-path-segment'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-sr-bidir-path'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-stamp-srpm'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7799'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
